In this video, I'm going to talk about
interesting slicer tricks that I believe
that you could also benefit a lot from.
All right, fellas. The first trick is
default selection in the slicers. What
do I mean by that? Take a look. So, here
I have like a mock dashboard, like a
pseudo dashboard. It's not even close to
a dashboard, but please take a look. So,
we have like a chart here and a card
visual here. And on the left we have a
slicer. The slicer has been built off
the calendar table. Currently I have the
year and the month in the slicer. Now
let's say for example the report goes
through a refresh. The next month the
April data kicks in. And at the moment
right now we have set the month to be
March. But you would want the dashboard
to auto update to the month of April on
the next refresh. How is that going to
be possible? Well, what you can do is
you can set up a clever trick and make
sure that the refresh date is actually
selected in the slicer by default. I'm
going to give you a rough idea as to how
do you make it work, whether you want to
make it work in Power Query or you want
to make it work in DAX. The idea is
pretty much the same. Let's just go take
a look. So, I'm going to hop over to my
calendar table right here. Pretty
standard calendar table. Couple of
columns, date, month, year, and quarter.
And I would like to create one
additional column right here. Let's just
call this column as current month. And I
first create a variable called the
refresh date. This date could be today's
date. This date could be the refresh
date of your model. This date could be
any date. For the moment, I'm just
picking up 2001, the month of 10, and
1st of October. That's what I'm picking
at the moment. Now, since I want that
date to be formatted on in only the year
and the month format, I have used a very
simple format function right here. And
I'm actually formatting the refresh date
in mmmmm and y y y y y y y y y y y y y y
y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y
y y y y y y y format order. Finally, I
build a very simple check. In that
check, all that I'm saying is that hey,
why don't you pick up this particular
date and for this particular date, you
do the same formatting month and year
and why don't you just check if that is
equals to the format of the current
date, the refresh date or not. If both
the formats are matching, that means
that we would like to be able to apply
that month as default selected slicer.
And finally I write the return
statement. And after the return
statement I say that hey if this
particular check that means the current
date and the refresh a month year is the
same. Then I would like to mark that as
the current month. Otherwise just give
me the month column which is this
particular column. That's pretty much
about it. Press enter and we are good to
go. All right I'm back on my slicer and
that's where I have the year and the
month. But hey, this time from the slice
of visual that we have, we would like to
be able to remove this particular month
as a column and get the column that we
have created instead. So I'm going to
remove this. So I can go ahead and go
right here and perhaps add the data and
say that please I'd like to get the
current month. Old habits do not go
easy. Nevertheless, once we have the
current month right here, you can see
that the current month currently marked
in our slicer is the current month right
here, which is October at the moment.
Let's just go and go ahead and I'm going
to go ahead in my calendar table and try
to change my date. So I'm back at my
calendar table and now if I say that the
current month has changed. Obviously
this is going to be automatically
detected through the today's date or
your refresh date or whatever that might
be. At the moment I'm picking up this
particular date as a manual date, but
I'm sure you can have a workar around
for this date to be either today's date
or the model refresh date. For now,
let's just change this date from the
month of 10 to the month of 11, which is
November. And obviously, the current
month has automatically changed. Now,
the question is, if we go back to our
visual, the dashboard should have
automatically changed the current month
from October to November. If I just go
back and take a look at that, you can
see that since I selected current month
right here, October now has
automatically been selected to the now
current month, which is nothing but
November. Now, this trick was obviously
done in DAX. If you know the way to do
that and if you set up calendar tables
or date tables in Power Query, I'm sure
you can figure out a way to do the same
thing in Power Query as well. The logic
remains the same. All that you have to
do is create another column to mark the
current date or the refresh date to
check against the calendar. You know
what's the hardest thing about learning
PowerBI? It is translation. The ability
to translate the DAX logic or the M
logic or data modeling into your own
scenario, your own industry with your
own data is really hard. And if you
learn that, that is when you have truly
learned how to use PowerBI into your own
business setting. And that is the reason
why we are launching PowerBI case
studies. These are case studies in HR,
in logistics, in finance, in supply
chain, every possible industry that you
can imagine. We going to build a case
study right from scratch. Understand the
moving parts of that industry, how the
data works, how the business logic
works, and then how do you transform
that into a working solution that you
can implement into your own business
setting. Apply all slices. If you take a
look at my visual right here, I have
product and I have region and I have
this matrix visual. Assume that the
current visual is somehow very very
slow. The queries are running very slow.
So what I want to do is I want to have
all the slicers applied first and then I
want to see the effect of those slices
sliced into my visuals. Well, how do I
do that? How do I pause the slicers?
That's what I'm trying to say. So at the
moment, if I just happen to click on a
shampoo or a hair gel or a cream, the
slicers get applied. But I don't really
want to do that. I want to first apply
all the slicers and then click on apply
slicers. Well, there is a button to
that. So, I'm going to go over to the
insert tab. In the insert tab, I have
the button right here. And I can click
on the apply slicers button. And once I
do that, I get this little button right
here. And now, what I'm going to do is
I'm going to start to apply the slicers.
And you're going to see that the table
is not going to change. So, I click on
Mumbai. I click on the therapy shampoo.
I click on the smoothe
oil. So, all of these. And you can see
that there is a little waiting icon next
to every single slicer. That means these
slicers are not applied yet. Now these
are going to be applied only when I
click on apply slices button and that is
also highlighted and now the slicers are
applied and you can see the change of
that in the visual. This is very very
helpful in case you are working with
slower queries in your model. Well guess
what there is also a clear slicers
button available in PowerBI and you can
do that to clear all the slicers off on
the screen. So I'm going to go over to
the insert once again again in the
buttons dropdown and pick up the clear
slicers button. I get that. I can place
that right here. Now, as soon as you
click right here on this particular
button, you're going to clear off all
the slicers off from the screen and the
visual is going to be absolutely
unfiltered. I just click that and you
can see that all the slices are gone and
the visual is absolutely unfiltered. The
fields parameter trick. I'm sure
everybody has worked with fields
parameter that lets you pick up a few
columns of your choice and add them as a
slicer. But did you know that you can
also add the values of those columns as
a slicer? Let me help you understand
what am I trying to say. So let's just
say that I have this simple table visual
right here and I have the first column
is year, month and then the total sales.
Now I would like to be able to slice
this visual either by the channel or by
the region. Both of these columns are
there in my sales table. So if I just go
take a look at my sales table, my region
and my channel are two columns of my
choice that I would like to place it as
a slicer and that should appear in the
slicer. So to do that I can obviously
use something like a fields parameter.
So in the insert tab, in the modeling
tab, sorry, I'm going to go to the new
parameter and I'll say fields parameter.
And this is just going to be ask me to
give a column name or a table name.
That's what I have done. And choose the
columns that I would want. So the first
column of my choice is channel. The
second column of my choice is region. I
do that. Add a slicer to this page.
Click on okay. And a slicer obviously
gigantic one is added to the page. And I
can push that off right here. Now
obviously if I just happen to click,
nothing is going to happen because this
slicer is not there in the visual. So
let's just add that. So I can just add
the column slicer off to the visual
right here and I can see all the regions
if I happen to click on region or if I
click on the channel. This is the
standard stuff that everybody knows
about. Now I would want to now add a
secondary slicer which is where I want
to take a look at the values of those
channels underneath here in the slicer.
Well, you can do that. So I can just
click on the slicer and ctrl + ctrl +v
and now I can change the properties of
the slicer right click on the columns
and I can say that hey instead of the
choice between the two columns which is
channel or the region I would want to
have the choice between the values of
those columns. So I can say show values
of the selected field. Click on that.
Now it is showing me the values in the
channel column or the values in the
region column and I can further filter
down the values like that. This is
pretty damn awesome.
Now the default behavior of the slicer
is to slice or filter the data. But you
can also use the slicer to be able to
highlight instead. Take a look. What do
I mean by that? Here I have a simple
table setup. So we have the products
name right here and we have the total
sales. On the right hand side I have a
slicer right here and I picked up a few
products right here. As soon as I click
the value in the slicer, the table
doesn't get filtered. However, it gets
highlighted instead. So if I were to
just maybe pick up another product right
here, I'm going to have four rows
highlighted. If I maybe keep on picking
up the products right here, it gets
highlighted instead. This can be very
helpful to highlight elements in a table
or in fact even in bar charts or column
charts. Let's just see how this is done.
All right, let's just start with the
native table visual that we have which
is the products and the total sales and
a slicer which is on the products table.
So if you look at the data model right
here, in the data model we have the
products table. Obviously we have the
calendar table and the sales table. Any
filter that comes in from the products
table right here will have the ability
to filter out the sales table. That
means it will filter not highlight. If I
were to just go back to my visual and
pick up any value right here, it's
actually going to filter down my table
and not highlight. To overcome this
problem, what we need is a disconnected
table. And using that disconnected
table, we're going to make a slicer.
Let's just see how that is done. I'm
going to go over to my data model right
here. And on the right, I have kind of
hidden this disconnected table, which I
can place it right here. And if you take
a look at the code for that disconnected
table, it's very, very simple. All that
I'm saying is that, hey, why don't you
go over to the products table, which is
this particular table. Go over to the
products column, remove the blanks, and
make a single column instead. and you
will have the list of all the SKUs, all
the product names right here. Now, since
this particular table is not connected
with any other table, any filters or
slicers applied on this column will not
be able to filter the sales table. And
that is nice. I'm going to go ahead and
revise my slicer to contain the column
from the disconnected table instead. So,
I'm just go right here in the visual,
remove this, add the data from the
disconnected table, and put the product
right in there. And once we have the
product, obviously if you were to now
click on any one of the products, it is
not going to filter the sales table or
the products table right here. And that
is nice. The second question comes is
that at the moment the filter is not
happening which is one problem that we
overcame. But how do we then highlight
it? How do we capture this particular
value right here and make this value
stand out in this table right here? For
that we'll have to use conditional
formatting and we'll have to write a
measure and use it as a conditional
formatting. Let's just go write that
measure. I'm going to go over to the
data and perhaps anywhere I can right
click and I can say that I'd like to
make a new measure. The name of the
measure can be highlight and the code is
reasonably logical. So I'm going to
write something like hey I'd like to
filter filter which table filter my
products table which is connected by the
way. And in this particular table, what
I'm trying to do is I'm trying to see
that how many of these products are
selected in this particular table or
not. So I'm going to use a selected
value function and selected value
function of the products table and the
product column which is the product
name. So essentially what I'm trying to
do is I'm trying to check that if this
particular product in the current filter
context, the current selected product is
that anywhere in the selected products
in the slicer or not. And for that I'm
going to use a very simple in function
and I'm going to say hey why don't you
check all the products which are there
in this particular table the
disconnected table this time. So
products disconnected and the products
and that is pretty good to go. Now at
the moment if you take a look I just
cannot return this measure in the in the
table right here because filter function
returns a table and you can't really
have a table in the table in the
measure. So I'm going to maybe wrap this
around in the count rows function. I'll
say, "Hey, why don't you count the
number of rows in the formula that is
returned by this function?" Close the
bracket and press enter. At the moment,
if I return the measure over to my
visual, I'm going to get something like
this. Every product that happens to be
selected in the slicer is marked with
one. That means yes, the products table
is left with just one row of data if
this particular bike wash dissolver is
selected. Again in this particular
filter context the products table is
left with one row of data if this
particular value is selected. So that's
pretty easy to do. At the moment I can
just make a very simple condition and
the condition is something like this.
Why don't we check? So let's just give
it this a variable. So variable is going
to be check and I am going to say
something like hey does the check
contain any more than one rows of table
or not? If that contains any more than
one rows of table I can use a color to
highlight. So I can say something like
return and I can say hey if the check is
greater than equal to a one in that case
why don't you just do something like an
orange color else don't do any color
press enter and this formula is already
dragged at the moment I get the text as
orange but I don't want the text as
orange however I would want the color as
orange I can remove this highlight from
the visual right here and instead use
the highlight in the conditional
formatting I'm going to go over to the
format in the format I'm going to go
over to sell elements. In cell elements,
I will activate the background color for
total sales. Activate that. And here I'm
going to use the FX to apply the color.
So total sales is going to be applied
with a field value. And the field value
is nothing but highlight. I will check
at that. Click on okay. And that gets
highlighted. But I'd like to highlight
the entire row. So I need to pick up the
second field as well. And again, I will
switch that over to the name of the
product, which is the first column right
here. I'm going to activate the
background color. Again, go over to the
field values. pick up the highlight
measure that I've written. Click on okay
and that is highlighted. Now if you were
to pick up any particular value right
here or even multiple values they get
highlighted instead. The same technique
can be used to highlight the bars of the
bar chart or the column charts as well.
Once you know the technique you can
apply it anywhere that you like. In the
next trick I'm going to talk about that
how can you set hierarchies while
working with field parameters. I'm sure
you have worked with field parameters in
the past. incredibly great feature to
natively select the measures in the
slicer. Let's just take a look at what
do I mean by setting up hierarchies. So
I have this table right here and in the
table I have the name of the product
against that I have some stupid
measures. So I have total sales which is
not so stupid. Then we have pseudo sales
commissions and some more commissions
right here. Now the first two I would
like to categorize them as my sales and
the second two I'd like to categorize
them as my earnings and for which I can
obviously set up let's say a fields
parameter. So I can just go in right
here and I can go over to the insert
tab. Where is that? Sorry modeling tab.
In the modeling tab I can click on new
parameter and I can click on the fields
parameter. In the fields parameter I can
say that hey my parameter is going to be
my KPI. That is the name and I can pick
up all the four measures right here.
Once you've picked up all the four
names, total sales, these are my
measures, total sales, pseudo sales,
commissions, and more commission. I can
obviously check on add the slicer to the
page, and click on create. And that is
going to create a little slicer right
here, which I can place it anywhere.
Once we have placed the slicer on the
page for the slicer to have effect on
this table, what we need to do is
obviously pick up the element of the
slicer and put that in the table. So for
now if I just go to the table I have all
of these four measures which I can
remove from here and instead I can have
the KPI that I have created which is
nothing but the table. I can just place
that table right here. Now that is
nothing significant. I'm sure you know
how to do that. And now the slicer takes
an effect on the table. But what instead
I would like to show you that in case I
need to mark the first two measures as
like in a folder or something and I'd
like to visually show that these are my
sales measures and the last two measures
are my earning measures. Then how can we
do that? Now whenever you try to create
a fields parameter you obviously get the
table right here and the table has got
these three default columns the KPI the
KPI fields and the KPI order. This is
dependent upon what you wrote in the
fields parameter. At the moment, if you
take a look at this table, this table
obviously is the first column is right
here. That is nothing but the second
column and that is nothing but the order
which is not really visible. That is the
third column. Now, nobody is stopping
you from creating more columns in the
table that we can instead use in the
slicer. So if I were to just go ahead
after the comma and say that this is
nothing but my sales measure and perhaps
copy that to the second row as well that
is again my sales measure that is
nothing but my earnings measure and I
can copy that and that can also again be
my earning measure. Now as I do that you
can see that we have a value four
created which obviously we can rename
that to a tag and now that tag can be
used to categorize slicers further. I
can just go over to my visual in the
KPI. I can have like a hierarchy. I can
just put that right here. And you're
going to see that the tag is at the
bottom which I can bring it up on the
top and put the KPI at the bottom. And
that is done. And you can see that now
we have earning and within earning we
have the commission and more commission.
And in the sales we have zero sales and
the total sales. I can pick up anything
to display that in my table. And that is
a nice way to categorize your KPIs in
case you would like to show them in a
certain hierarchy or in a more
folderized manner.